Hey, this is Brendan Sanderson's writing
lecture series. This is week two on the
publishing industry. I delve a lot into
agents and in pitching your book and in
going to conventions. So hopefully this
will be helpful for you. Next week is
our last week, so come back for that
one. All right, welcome to writing
science fiction and
fantasy. Uh this is our second lecture
on the business of writing. This is also
going to be a bit of a fire hose like
last week. Uh hopefully there'll be a
little more time for questions this week
than there was last week. All right, so
if you'll remember last week, we talked
through kind of the history of
publishing and what publishing
departments do. Uh we did focus a lot on
sci-fi fantasy and afterwards I'm like I
probably should mention that the other
genres were also growing up at the same
time, right? Uh it wasn't just Tolken uh
that kicked off kind of the hard
coverver uh boom for uh for publishing.
I mean we got Agatha Christie in there.
We've got Ian Fleming in there. Um right
like people are writing in all of the
kind of traditionally like you got
Georgia O'Hare. Uh these traditionally
kind of a little more lowbrow um genres
were coming of age and then we
eventually hit the modern age with the
modern hardcover blockbuster book. So
let's talk I'm actually going to do
these a little out of order. Let's talk
about how people used to break into the
industry. Uh for context, once upon a
time in science fiction and fantasy, if
you wanted to break in, the thing that
you did was write short
stories. Uh this is because the pulp
magazines were the big seller uh of
science fiction fantasy. A lot of the
people who were reading it didn't have a
lot of disposable income. They were u
reading these magazines and they were
reading a lot of short stories. And this
is where the golden age of science
fiction really kind of came about. Uh
your Azimovs and your Clarks and these
people were all publishing in the
magazines. And so if you wanted to break
in, the general advice was go sell some
things in short fiction markets. And
then once you've proven yourself in
short fiction, you can then start
putting in your cover letters. We'll
talk about cover letters and um and
queries and things. You start putting in
them. Hey, um I uh have published an
analog and FNSF and blah blah blah and
this is my first novel. It's about this.
You'd have these really great writing
credentials to sell your book through
query letter. Back then, you often
didn't need an agent. Um remember how I
talked about last week all these little
publishing houses that used to be
separate? They got gobbled up. Well,
when they got gobbled up, particularly
the science fiction ones, they usually
left all of the structure intact, the
publishers and things. And these were
all people who were all friends of each
other who'd grown up going to
conventions together. I think I told you
about uh did I tell you about Mosha, my
editor last time? Like he just showed up
at a house once and they're like, "Oh,
read for us." Right? You're a nerd.
Read. Tell us what you think of this. Um
and a lot of these people knew each
other very well. And in fact, they knew
the authors that were consistently
publishing in the magazines. And so when
someone who had been consistently
publishing wrote their debut novel, all
of the publishers would be interested.
Uh and generally that was your funnel.
Well, in the 80s things started to
change. The hard coverver Blockbuster
took over uh as the main way people were
reading. Uh readers had more disposable
income. They were buying full novels.
And it turns out that what the market
really wanted was that because that
started to eat away at the short fiction
market. When I was breaking in, a lot of
people were still saying, "Well, have
you published any short fiction?" And a
lot of us breaking at the time were
like, "We don't read the magazines. None
of us have ever looked at one." We grew
up reading Robert Jordan. We didn't grow
up reading uh analog science fiction.
And so because of that um we started
just submitting novels straight out and
the industry didn't quite know what to
do with us, right? Because this method,
this pipeline to publication was no
longer functioning as it once had
because people weren't reading or
writing short fiction at the levels that
they used to. And uh in fact, the
magazines, you know, they there are
still several of the of the good ones
out there. I do recommend them. Writing
short fiction is still a a perfectly uh
fantastic thing to do, but you should
read it and write it because you love
it, not because it's an avenue to break
in. It still can be if you are good at
short fiction, but it is no longer the
main way to break in. During about this
time, agents in sci-fi fantasy really
started to come to prominence because
suddenly the novel was the main way and
you had to find it in the slush pile.
This wasn't the only economic pressure
on the pub on the authors and publishers
that for agents to rise, but it was
definitely a contributing factor in my
opinion. And so suddenly all of these
novels are being submitted and the
publishers are overwhelmed by them
because now they have to take these
submissions. There's not this this
apprenticeship and they have to find the
diamonds in the rough. They start
offloading more and more of the work to
agents who start during this time to be
the slush pile
readers because the publishers get
overwhelmed. About this time in the late
'9s, agents started charging more. They
used to be 10%. And we'll talk about
agents next. They then moved into
charging 15% which is now the standard.
That is off the top of everything you
earn that you publish through them. Um,
which is generally going to be all of
your novels. agents generally don't care
about short fiction. You can do whatever
you want with that, but a short fiction
piece will often earn you pizza money,
not rent money.
Okay? So, the uh the agents start taking
over and the publishers, they kind of
like this. Like imagine you're an editor
and you're there and you're like, I used
to have this slush pile to the ceiling
full of terrible books and now instead I
don't have to read that. an agent has
already read through all of that and
brings me the best
stuff. And this started to really become
the way that you broke in. I broke in in
2003. I was at the tail end of the p the
time when you could break in without an
agent. Um, and I broke in through
networking back in the day like in the
80s and 90s in order to have a new style
of apprenticeship. A lot of the
breakouts came from people who went to
conventions, hobnobbed with the editors
and agents, started to make a name for
themselves just by being, you know,
somebody who was at the conventions that
talked intelligently uh about, you know,
science fiction, fantasy. When I took
this class um in 2000, Dave Wolverton
said to me, he's like, "Your writing is
really good, Brandon. You finished six
novels. You need to be publishing." I'm
like, "Well, how do I do that he's like,
"All right, I want you to go to World
Con and World Fantasy Convention and to
the Nebula Award weekend whenever it's
in New York. That's where you'll find
the agents and editors." So, I started
doing that that year. I actually stayed
with Scar's cousins brother. Scar's
brother. Scar uh and I and a couple
others went and slept on the floor of
his brother's house. uh cuz Scar's from
Jersey and we figured that's better than
paying uh New York hotel prices cuz the
Nebula Awards were there and we went to
the Nebula Awards like that summer. This
one always throws me off. It moves. Um
you know, I'm used to being able to
lounge back and and pontificate. Uh we
go we sleep on the floor. We bought
umbrellas. Someone stole our umbrellas.
Um we went to the Nebula Awards very
awkwardly cuz Dave said, "Go sit in the
bar. That's where people chat." And
we're like, we're sitting there with our
sprites. Hi. And everyone is super
friendly. Like not everyone was
drinking. They're just there in the
hotel bar where this is happening. I sat
down next to next to an editor at tour,
not knowing it, and just started up a
conversation uh and said, "Hey, can I
send you a book?" Like I I make it sound
like I was cool. It was more like
um right. And he said, "Yeah, sure. Send
me a book." Uh he never got back to me
on that. I joke that there's still a
copy of White Sand somewhere in the at
tour that they're going to dig it out,
you know, underneath some cabinet
somewhere and be like, "A Sanderson book
that we haven't
published. Stop the presses." Um, right.
Uh, but I sent him that and then I went
up to the like little cocktail party up
up above and I met an agent named Joshua
Bilmis who said, "Yeah, go ahead and
send me something." And I sent him
something and he rejected it. But he
rejected it, saying, "This is actually
pretty good. Send me your next thing."
Um, that next uh year after that, I went
to world to world fantasy in Montreal.
Scar wasn't at this one, but uh Dan and
Peter were. And Ben, for some reason,
um yeah, you guys know Ben. Um he's our
he's our friend who's a computer science
guy that just is beused by all these
nerds. Um and so we went there and at a
party I met Mosha. Um like and I pitched
him a book and he said, "Send me that
book." Moshe eventually bought that
book. Uh Joshua I called up when uh when
Mosha had said, "Hey, I want to buy
this." And I said, "Hey, you gave me a
really good rejection. Uh you've read a
couple of my books now. You've rejected
them all, but there's one that to wants.
Are you interested in handling
negotiations for me?" And he said, "Free
money?" "Yes." Well, he actually said,
"Send me the book. Make let me make sure
it's good." Uh he read the book. He's
like, "All right, it's pretty good.
that's better than the ones you sent me
um before. So yeah, we'll do this. And
so he handled negotiations. Um and
that's how I broke in. This is again
kind of the last generation where that
was possible. Um as the old guard in
publishing uh got older and retired, the
new people that they hired actually like
had corporate experience and understood
like being part of a big publishing
company. and they all basically moved to
taking the agent submissions, right? Um,
and the agents, a really good agent is
more than just somebody who submits your
book. They submit your book to the right
place. So, the agents all learned that
the best thing they could do was be
taking editors out to lunch. They would
learn what the editors have bought
recently, what they're looking for, what
they like, and they would keep
relationships with all the editors at
all the publishers. So when the right
book came in, the agent would be able to
target it at the right people and
hopefully improve their sales numbers or
their sales percentage, the percentage
of selling a book. So these days, that's
kind of how it
is. Selling without an agent is
virtually impossible. Uh there are a few
places you can do it. Bane books will
still take one uh on agent. In fact, Jim
Bane, who founded it, hated agents and
those who have taken over uh for Jim
have um have kind of maintained that. Uh
Bane is kind of what you might call a
medium-sized press. It's not a small
press. It's not one of the big uh five.
It's its own kind of thing. So, um you
know, Bane is an outlier. There's a
there are other ones in children.
Scholastic is an outlier. Scholastic is
not one of the big five, but it plays
like one. Bang kind of plays like one
only in sci-fi fantasy. Uh they tend to
have lower advances, but they tend to
support their authors very well. So
that's kind of, you know, uh if you read
Bane books, you'll know what kind of
style. They're a little bit more pulpy,
a little more sword and sorcery/ space
opery, but they'll do anything. Um so
right now, that's basically your options
in sci-fi fantasy. You have the imprints
of the big five and you have Bane. Uh
there are some various small presses. In
general, I do not recommend small
presses for people who are breaking in
if they intend to want to have a career
in science fiction and fantasy. There
are good small presses. I have published
with Tachon and I had a wonderful
experience with them. There are other
presses like Tachon that with the right
book, like a novella or just in the
right circumstances, an agent might say
yes, let's submit to them. And a lot of
these you can submit to without an
agent. Also that said, the advances are
small. Their distribution tends to be um
a little bit smaller and it is very hard
to earn a living with a small press. Not
impossible to leverage that into being a
best-selling author, but I recommend
that authors if they want to go
traditionally go for the go to the top
or that they independently publish. the
the middle ground is generally not
something I recommend just because the
small presses for how good some of them
can be. Um and again I have published
with Tachion and it was the right thing
to do for for that specific book. They
did the print version of Emperor Soul
and I maintained the ebook rights and
sold the ebook myself. Um main reason
that I say to avoid them is because um
generally because of the current
environment with indie publishing. Um
you're going to be asked to do the same
things for a small press that you have
to do indie publishing. Do all the
publicity yourself and things like this,
which means that if you're going to have
to do that anyway, you might as well
independent publicly publish and make a
larger cut off of the smaller amount of
money. Um your your mileage may vary.
All right. So, we've kind of covered
that these days you break in with
agents. What is an agent in the
publishing industry? Agents have a bad
reputation in the music and uh film
industry. Generally,
uh publishing or u book agents do not
have that bad reputation with their um
with their authors. Um I have had an
excellent experience with mine. Most
authors I know asterisks we'll get to um
you know the exceptions have very good
experience with their agents and agents
are generally highly regarded. Um
they're New Yorkers a lot of them but
not all of them. Um and they tend to uh
they tend to talk like New Yorkers in my
experience.
Um so what does this mean? Well an agent
in books is really kind of four
different things. All right. On one
hand, there's the thing we've talked
about. They sell your book. That is one
of their main jobs is as a new author to
take the book and be able to target it
to the right publishers. They also are
one small part business
manager. So, an agent will give you
career advice. An agent will give you
guidance. Um because these days they act
as a slush pile. They also uh tend to be
doing developmental editing which is a
thing that the old guard in publishing
does not like at all. And in fact uh
Heinline would probably if he knew and
were capable would climb out of the
grave and start slapping us all around
for letting agents do developmental
editing on books. uh because his opinion
would be only the person giving you
money has a right to tell you to change
anything and even then if you don't like
it you should scream at them till they
till they change their mind. Um I'm very
opinionated on on revisions and things
and I like to pass that along. People
who don't like agents this is a sticking
point. uh where that asterisk comes from
it is because some um some authors part
particularly indie authors say um I
don't want to do developmental edits for
someone who's not an editor buying the
book and number two they worry about
conflict of interest meaning an agent uh
needs to keep a good relationship with
all of these editors in order to keep
selling books go agents are worried
about submitting books that they're not
you know that they haven't had some
development al editing ex u work on
because they only want to be submitting
the best things to the editors so they
maintain that relationship. So the
relationship with the editor to some
authors becomes a sticking point that
the agents therefore are not um
following the author's needs they are
following the editor's needs. So those
are kind of the two of the sticking
points. Um an agent will be an expert in
contract negotiations. In publishing,
you should not need a separate attorney
than an agent until you get big enough
that Hollywood is paying attention. And
then you probably want one. Um, but
until then, an agent can do all of your
contract negotiations with the um with
the editor and they should know how to
do that and what to get. In fact, the
big agencies will have already
negotiated certain things that they
always get that will go right in your
contract automatically. Okay. Um and
then the fourth thing fourth thing an
agent um can be is your friend in the
publishing
industry. Um your editor should be your
friend but the moment contract
negotiations start or something's wrong
that you disagree with the editor then h
you know they work for the publisher and
not for you. Because of this you should
have a good relationship with your
editor. You should want to do the
revisions that they're suggesting
because you should want to try them out.
But if they ask for a revision that you
try out and it is not good for the book,
the agent is the person who goes to bat
for you and says, "No, they're not
changing this." Um, some examples of
things that my agent has done for me. My
agent kept keeps track of what the
bookstores order as their orders for his
uh for his books independently of what
the uh publisher says. So when Elasters
was coming out, Barnes & Noble had
decided on like an eightbook copy order
for the paperback, which was really
good. The hard cover had sold really
well. They put in that was eight copies
per store. Joshua knew this is back when
bookstores actually sold books. Um now
they sell Legos,
right? And then they then they upsell
you to books. Um the bookstores were the
way that people bought books. Um, as an
aside, um, one time I tried I went to
every bookstore in San Diego and, uh,
one of my marketing tactics was I took a
big box of paperbacks of Alantress and
I'd go in and I'd say, "Hey, who's your
book seller on staff who loves sci-fi or
fantasy?" And they'd be like, "Oh, yeah.
You know, it's Sandy right over here."
Every time someone comes in that's a
science fiction nerd, we send them to
her. And so I went to her and I said,
"Hey, will you I'll give you a free copy
of my book if you'll read it." And these
people were just ecstatic, right?
Because they usually weren't the
managers. Uh they were just there
because they love books and they didn't
get the free books that got sent. So
they get the free books. I managed to
get to 36 bookstores in San Diego during
a two-day period. I think there's now
eight. Um it changes, right? And these
were like we've had a contraction in the
number of uh bookstores, but regardless
uh Launchress, they took eight copies.
Joshua went to his sources and found
that they were only getting four. Torah
had told us eight. Joshua went to Torah
and said, "You promised us eight
copies." They're like, "Well, it wasn't
a promise. It was a" He's like, "Go
check the paperwork. What did they write
down?" And he argued and argued. Finally
went and checked. They're like, "All
right, they wrote down four. They're
taking eight." And then eight copies of
Launcher showed up in every bookstore.
Um, this is the sort of thing that
Joshua does. when um the cover for the
paperback of Misborn was really bad and
I think I told you guys about this um
that that was like the closest my career
ever came to
collapsing. Um we got very angry and by
we I mean Joshua became the biggest pain
in the rear that tour to had ever dealt
with until they agreed to put a new
cover on and try something new and that
saved my career. Um now I was the one
that said we need a new cover but I
didn't have to be the bad guy. Joshua
got to be the bad guy. So, the agent is
the person who will always be in your
corner um when you need to kind of turn
a failank toward the publisher on those
hopefully rare occasions where you're in
disagreement with the publisher, but
you're always going to be in
disagreement with them during contract
negotiations. Um, I have watched people
in publishing swap from my best buddy
sitting at dinner laughing to me
bringing up a contract point to
instantly they are a different person
because now they have to put on their
marketing hat and now they have to
protect their business against me. And
so instant change of de demeanor and so
the agent is there to deal with that so
that you don't have to. Okay. In
exchange for that, you will generally
sign a contract with an agent that says
you will use them for all of your
novels. And every contract they
negotiate, they will get 15% off the
top. This generally means that the
publishers will send the agent the
check. They will take 15% and send 85 to
you. If that bothers you, they you can
have the publisher split it. It's
actually really nice to have the agent
do it because a good agent, one of the
things they will also do is sell your
book in other countries. Uh America, one
of our primary exports is entertainment.
Um and what we tend to do is sell books
worldwide. Uh my books are in, I don't
know, 29 30 countries or something like
that. Uh Joshua had the rights to a
launcher sold to other countries before
the book came out in the US. Uh and
early on this money was small, right? He
does it for bragging rights. If you get
$250 for these rights or those rights,
they're not really making him much
money. Uh for foreign rights, generally
an agent will take 20%. They'll take 10%
for themselves and a foreign agent who
handles negotiations in language will
take 10%. And the US agent will build
these relationships with all these
foreign agents. So it's like 250 bucks,
you know, they make $50 split between
two of them or whatever. 25 bucks is not
worth the time, but the kind of mark of,
hey, we sold it in this this language is
really important. And if you do that 20
times, that $200 that you're getting
suddenly becomes real money to the
author even though it's not much to the
agent. And so a good agent knows this is
kind of like how authors particularly
newer in their career sometimes survive.
Uh and Joshua was very big on this,
still is. But this is like uh a gold,
you know, standard he holds up for his
agency is we sell everywhere and we make
our authors um a decent amount of money
just off the foreign rights. And so in
doing that's kind of money I lived on. I
told you guys that I sold my first
contract was for Alonsus was $10,000.
Joshua negotiated up from 5,000 to
10,000. So they offered 5,000 for one
book. He got me 20,000 for two books.
But that's paid out in uh like four
chunks. So you get like a certain amount
on signing, a certain amount on turnin
of the hard cover, a certain amount of
uh of turn of publication of the
paperback, a certain amount on
publication of the hard cover. I guess
those two are reversed, but you know
what I'm saying. You get these little
chunks strung out. And because that 20
grand didn't even come in one year, a
lot of that money that he got me as an
agent um is what what I lived on. That
and the sweet sweet income of my school
teacher wife. who public school teacher
wife at a middle school. Uh she was she
was my sugar mama at that time.
Um so this is what an agent is going to
do. They are investing in hopefully you
becoming a Brandon Sanderson because
right now you know we we will have six
figure incomes out of some of these
foreign markets uh approaching seven
figure out of uh some of the markets.
And so because of that, he's able to
have worked so hard at the beginning.
Now he kind of just gets to get that
money. Um though you would say, "What
does an agent do for you when you're at
level?" The number of things we have to
yell and argue about are much bigger. So
he still earns his money. Um but a lot
of what they're doing is hoping that the
small author will become the big author
and things like this.
Um
so you generally are going to need an
agent. If you go traditionally, you can
use an entertainment lawyer
instead. Very few authors do this, but
it is a possibility that I should
mention. You pay them by the hour, a
billable hour instead. They negotiate
your contract and they handle only the
contract negotiation part. You're in
charge of then foreign sales, um, being
the bad guy and all these things. If you
feel good doing this, you can do it. I
think Lee Modiset, who was a local
author, did it himself for a while. He
was in politics and then he was an
attorney and uh nobody wanted to
negotiate with him and he made them and
he got good contracts himself and then
he'd have an entertainment attorney look
it over to make sure and uh things like
this. A lot of indie authors still use
agents for foreign deals. Very difficult
to sell foreign. Uh the indie markets
just are not huge there. um and the
ebook markets are not as big overseas as
they are here. This is generally because
the EU um has put laws in place that
that uh forbid ebooks from undercutting
print books in order to protect
bookstores. Because of that, ebooks just
are not a thing in a lot of countries.
Um if you're going to spend the same
amount for it, people will just go to
the bookshop and buy it, which is the
purpose of the thing. But it also has
kind of stifled a lot of growth in the
industry. uh you don't have people who
are a able to go read $3 ebooks uh
because all the ebooks are 30 bucks. Um
and so uh it's kind of uh strangled that
but it you know you know there are there
are gives and takes to every every law
made and so the ebook market it there
are a few places where it does all right
but in general the US is where ebooks
are huge. Um, they do fine in the UK,
but US, no, no one's like us. Everybody
has laws preventing e um ebooks from
selling uh what they do here. Um, so you
will probably need an agent. How do you
get an agent? Well, we'll go into
pitching your book next. Let's stop and
ask questions. The fire hose of what an
agent does, what they're for. Um, I I
should mention that you'll sign that
contract with an agent. The contracts
with agents should be very easy to get
out of when you're signing your contract
with an agent. Um, let me let me give
you a few things. Number one, only
submit to agents or agencies whose books
you can find in the
bookstores right now. You should be able
to go to the bookstore and find that
agency's books. Buy new authors in the
bookstores right now. If you can't, you
shouldn't probably be submitting to that
agent. Okay.
Um, Joshua always likes me to give the
warning. There are accreditation agent
um agencies for agents. You do not have
to belong to one. Good agents don't and
badge agents do. Your best um two
weapons in finding a good agent is have
do they have uh books by new authors in
the bookstores right now. And number
two, do their authors say good things
about them? That's basically how you do
your research on agents. Go to the
fronts of books, see if they they
acknowledge their agent. try to see that
author at a convention, ask what they
think of their agent. Most of the time,
you will not be able to submit to the
big author's agent. Joshua takes almost
no uh new clients, but Joshua has a
bunch of sub agents that he mentors. A
new agent at an established agency is
still a fine place to submit. Even if
that agent's books aren't out yet, they
will be mentored by um a very uh
established agent. Joshua did this for
Scott Meredith. Scott Meredith retired,
all of his agents went and started their
own agencies. Uh when Joshua retires,
all of his agents will go start their
own agencies. And that's kind of how
agenting works these days. Uh generally,
your agents are people who've
apprenticed under other agents. Uh the
good ones. All right. So, watch out for
scams. Maybe we'll talk more about that
later. Any questions on what I've said
so far? We'll go here and then over
here. Should you ever have to pay for an
agent to read your book? Excellent
question. Should you have to pay for an
agent to read your book? Um, no.
Asterisks. Uh, there are a few times if
you are paying for a pitch session with
an agent at a conference, that's okay.
All right. Uh, that money generally goes
to the conference to defay the cost of
bringing the agent out and things like
that. Um, generally stay very far away
from reading fees. Once in a while there
is a legit one. Sometimes there's a
legit contest that has like a cheap like
$5 reading fee to keep the submissions
down and things, but agents should be
doing this for the industry. They should
not be charging reading fees and they
sure certainly be shouldn't be uh
exorbitant ones. Uh unless you're indie
published, money flows toward the
author. No author should have to spend
anything except postage um or you know
going to a conference or something. Any
publisher who asks you for money, scam.
agents who ask you for money scam
asterisks where if it's a very small
amount once in a while legit agents do
it but almost never do you hear of it
should be a huge red flag um if they ask
you for money uh I know early on you
said that it used to be 10% it's now 50%
yes 15 yeah can you renegotiate a
performance-based um cut depending on
how many sales you get yeah good
question can you negotiate a
performance-based cut depending on how
many sales you get the answer is yes if
you get big enough you can negotiate
anything very difficult to do as a new
author and I wouldn't even broach it as
a new author but once you you sell if
you become very big you can generally
you will have a good enough relationship
with your agent and you'll see like I
have never done this and I am one of the
biggest uh authors in the business
Joshua has earned his money now Joshua
doesn't take a cut from our Kickstarters
right he doesn't take a cut of of some
of these things, but there are very
difficult things I've asked Joshua to do
that he's been able to do and he
deserves that money. He, you know,
picked me up very early. And one of the
nice things I should mention about
Joshua is he didn't take 15% cuz I had
already sold the book. He said, "All
right, um, this contract, you did all
the work. I'm only taking 10%." And then
he bumped it up to 15 after he was
negotiating, like you know. But my first
contract, he only took 10%, which I
always thought was uh was nice of him
because he's like, "You already sold the
book. I can't take the full agent uh
commission on this." Um so yeah, but you
can it has been done before. It will be
done again. You get there, you can do
what you want. Yeah. Uh back here, um
you mentioned a lot about going to
writer conferences. Um, I was wondering
like how would you recommend investing
in something? Yes, that's uh that's
point number four. Cons is uh not cons,
it means conferences. I just didn't want
to try to spell conference and get it
wrong. There's all there's an E in there
that I that I mess up. Um, but yeah, so
let me get back to that one as my last
point. All right. All right. Other
questions over here and then we'll come
back to you and then we'll go over
there. Do you have any advice for those
want to become agents. Advice if you
want to become an agent. Um,
so almost all agenting is done in New
York. This is because the agents are
taking the editors out to dinner, right?
And out to lunch and things like this.
There are reputable agents who don't
live in New York. They generally moved
out of New York after they established
themselves, right? Um, and so you can
find good agents all around the country,
but for a new agent, you're going to
have to move to New York. they do look
at the publishing programs at NYU and
Colombia um and things like this. Uh
they're going to look for somebody who
has a keen eye for picking out
marketable fiction. Um and you know, uh
the agents that Joshua has hired, like
he got several from bookstores. He would
go to bookstores and he'd say, "Who do
you recommend? Who's new?" and he'd read
the book and he would he found the
people who were recommending to him to
the books that he would have bought and
then he started hiring them as his sub
agents but others came through the
programs he just does an internship he
offers an internship a bunch of people
apply this is generally how people make
it into publishing is through
internships both editing and agenting a
lot of agents start as editors and then
become agents not all of them uh but you
know tip is go to New York and start
becoming part of the community there and
start applying to the internships. Uh
it's a very hard road. Peter Strom, my
editorial uh VP, tried it for two years
in New York, h basically sucked all of
his savings away, never made any
inroads, and had to move uh back and
eventually got a job in California
working for a manga company as an
editor. So, he wasn't trying to be an
agent, he was trying to be an editor. Uh
agenting, you are going to generally the
agents are a little more swave than the
editors. So, uh, being someone who's
good with people and can negotiate and,
you know, that sort of thing is a really
good like editors don't have to be good
at that. Agents do. So, um, that's what
I'd recommend. All right. There's one
over here. Yeah. Um, when you mentioned
the agent contract, you said that you
signed that they get 15% off the top and
they get rights to your next books to
represent. So, yes, let me dig into that
more. They are basically representing
you as a person in all novels. Now, you
can make it some people have a different
agent for YA and adult as long as that's
done up front. Um, you know, agents tend
to be okay with it. Uh, it doesn't
happen as often because usually an
agency has a YA specialist and an adult
specialist and this and you just use the
same agency. Uh, it's just you have
different like Eddie at Jabberwocki does
my YA stuff. Um, right. And so um but
they are representing you. Meaning if
you're going to release a book that
falls under the agency agreement, which
is generally everything, but it might
just be you're going to send it to them
and they're going to represent you. If
you don't like how they do things, you
basically divorce them. You send them a
letter and say, "You're no longer my
agent." That's the end of it. That's all
you have to do. They will still collect
royalties on every contract they
negotiated for you as long as that
contract lasts. and they will continue
to send it to it to you. And I I know I
remember I left one thing out. It's
sometimes nice to have the agent get all
the money rather than having the
publisher split it because um I get
money from like like I said 30 different
countries and a bunch of different
audiobook uh things and three publishers
in the US and this it all comes to
Joshua. He then cuts me a check with
itemized sort of stuff. Um oh and here's
another thing where they charge you.
They charge you postage like when
they're shipping out your books to
people. Um, but that should come out of
their cut once they sell the book. So
Joshua never charged me anything until
he sold the book, but then there was
like a couple of hundred for shipping
books to the to across the world that
came out of the first check. Um, it's
never been more than a couple hundred
bucks, but we get an itemized thing. Um,
and then during tax season, you get a
1099. you get a single $1099 from an
agent. That is so much easier if you're
doing your own taxes than inputting
like, yes, I made
$75 from the Arabic rights and now I
have to go, do we have a tax treaty with
uh with this country? How do I fill out
a form for having, you know, like all
this stuff? It's all complicated, but a
1099 is so nice. Um so that's one of the
the reasons uh this does offer a point
of failure uh for the agent meaning the
agent could keep your money and you know
uh what's what's the kids say gaslight
you um and there have been notable
instances of agents you know keeping the
money like Joshua has in his contract
you must be sent the money any money we
get for you must be sent within 10
business days he's just got that in his
contract so that they just wire the
money. Basically, it's within a day or
two of them getting it. So, they're
earning interest on their author's
money's money, right? Um, but an agent
can do stuff like that. An agent can
cook the books um and things like that.
An agent will get a royalty statement
from the publisher every 6 months, which
will detail every sale and the royalties
you made on it. And then they should
pass that along to you. She rolls her
eyes. She hasn't gotten hers yet. um
they should pass that along to you that
you can then break down exact sales uh
and you can have your publisher send
send you that. You can uh you can audit
the agent and I do recommend uh
generally you should not consider your
agent your full-on business manager. You
should be in charge of your business.
You should be watching what your sales
are. You should be making sure that the
numbers are right because the agents are
good, but they can make mistakes and
it's your business, not theirs. When you
become an author, you are starting a
small business and you should treat it
as such. The IRS will treat it as such.
So, you should Okay, you are now a small
business owner. The moment you make more
than whatever it is, 500 bucks. I am not
a tax uh person. Go to your tax people.
But wherever it is, what you told me
it's 600 now. Whenever you make past
hobbyist income, you then essentially
have a small business. Uh even if you
haven't incorporated, uh we can talk
about stuff like that, but there you
are. All right. Over here, just going to
say, what's your opinion on submitting
manuscripts and publishing through
Shadow Mountain? What's my opinion on
Shadow Mountain? Shadow Mountain is a
lot like Bane. It is a viable option
that you have here that uh that others
don't have, and it plays like one of the
big guys in a small realm. Um, so Shadow
Mountain uh tends to have worse
contracts and worse advances, but Bane
tends to be the same way. If you know
what you're doing and you either have a
good agent or you ask someone like me,
you we can get the bad clauses out. Um,
and uh, maybe I'll go over what the bad
clauses are here for you. Um, I do
recommend Shadow Mountain. Everyone that
I've known that's published there has
had at least a good, if not excellent,
experience. And they are what we call a
regional press rather than a small
press. and they do a good job. So, if
you are lucky enough to uh to have an
offer on a middle-grade or YA book with
Shadow Mountain, which for those
watching online, that's a regional press
that's here in Utah that focuses on uh
middle grade and YA mostly. Um I do
recommend um taking that. Uh I know Mole
has had a good time with them. Um so,
but he's not the only one. Uh they do a
decent job. Um, all right. Let's let's
write on the board causes to watch out
for in publishing contracts.
Okay. All right. So, I'm going to I'm
going to Okay, we got to get to pitching
and conventions. We got
time. All right. Things you should keep
out of your contracts. Number one,
remember our royalty rates from last
time. You should be looking for those
royalty rates or better. Okay. We won't
go into that uh in depth. You should
keep
rights to
world slashc
characters.
Okay. do. I've seen well-meaning small
presses and even horror stories of large
presses that should know better where
they try to get the rights to
world/caracters for sequels. Run. Well,
don't run away. If it's a big publisher,
just have your agent scream at them and
they'll feel embarrassed because they
shouldn't go in no contract and they
know it.
Um, they are allowed to have first
refusal rights on your next book. We
talked about those last week, right? Did
I nod? Yes. I talked about first
refusal. Good. No. Someone's saying no.
Someone's saying yes. Yeah, I did. Go
watch. Yeah. So, right at first refusal
means that the publisher can have the
right to see your next book. That's
different from owning the rights to the
characters, right? that it's okay if
they say, "I would like to have rights
to first refusal on your next um adult,
you know, book book for the adult
audience." Um, try to keep that right
first refusal as narrow as possible. Um,
like I put in my books, you can see the
next Stormlight book and have rights of
first refusal. You can't have my next
fantasy book, right? Um, I keep it to
series. Uh, they can be hard-nosed when
you're a new author on this. It's okay
to sign a rights of first refusal on
next novel. Keep it to next novel. they
they don't want, you know, and if most
of them will agree to next novel for the
same market. So, if you write a
middlegrade, they don't have to see it
if you've published an epic fantasy. And
I recommend that, but they should not
get rights to your world and character.
They should not get your copyright. They
should be able to publish the book for
life of copyright, but it should
copyright to you. And they usually
register that for you. You send a book
to the Library of Congress. Um, I think
is how you do it. Am I right? I don't
know. You wouldn't know. Peter would
know. Um, so all right.
Um, they
should not be keeping uh uh film
rights. No p book publisher has any idea
what to do with your film rights.
Generally, they will slip something in
all of them that say, "If you sell film
rights, we get 50% of it is generally
what they'll put in." And then agents
will laugh at them and they'll chuckle
along nervously and strike it out. Um,
this should just not be in any
publishers don't do anything with film
rights. They just want to make free
money. Uh, your film rights are yours.
Okay?
They should
um they shouldn't keep your foreign
rights. Oh no, I have to spell foreign.
Ei. No. Yeah. Okay. I did it right that
time. Wow.
Oh well. Clapping for the professional
author knowing how to
spell. Is the bar that low?
Um so um you should keep your foreign
rights. Exceptions. I think I mentioned
this last year. you um selling North
American Spanish rights to particularly
a YA middle-grade um um um publisher,
totally fine. You're not going to be
able to do much with your North American
Spanish, but try to keep your South
American and your uh Europe European
Spanish rights. Um those are decent
markets. Uh you can let go of world
English rights. Some publishers just
will not let you have world English. Uh,
world English is um all the rights that
are English-speaking countries um
outside of North America and the
Philippines. North American rights
includes Philippines. If you need to
know why, uh go to history class. Um
just like uh world English uh rights
include India. Um which just basically
means world English is uh British
Commonwealth minus Canada. Um and the
right to like usually both can sell on
the continent. I think anyone who has
any rights can sell on the continent.
But for instance, tour can't sell my
books in the UK, Australia, um Ireland
um or India. Both can sell in uh in
foreign markets, foreign language
markets. But the world English market uh
the UK has. You're allowed to I say
allowed. You can do whatever you want,
but some publishers will not let you
keep World English. So, you kind of just
have to bend on that sometimes. You did,
right? Yeah. Um I almost did. Joshua was
adamant and finally they let go. Um so,
you should keep your foreign rights.
These are kind of like your big ones,
right? These are your big uh get this
out of your contract sort of stuff if it
happens to be in there. You would love
to keep audio.
They don't let you do this very often
anymore.
Um, if you can keep them, sell them to a
separate audiobook company. You're going
to have a hard time doing this in your
first contract these days. Used to be
easy. Um, now audio is such a big
percentage of the market that they have
mandates from above that they can't let
go of audio. Uh, anything else I should
put up here?
Um, we've talked about non-compete. Oh,
yeah. Non-compete. Non-compete is above
the
line. They started to put non-compete
contracts in. Maybe I'm an old fogy and
this is one you can't get out, but I
consider that just like morally
reprehensible that they put a
non-compete clause in. Like they should
have your right of first refusal. That
should be enough. There should be no
sort of non-compete. And I can I think
those non-compete clauses in contracts
across the board in a lot of industries
are just deemed illegal. and they don't
stand up in court. You should just Yeah,
I can't believe any agent would let uh
one of these slip, but they do. Um so,
uh try not to have a non-compete clause.
Um you should be able to write you
should be able to write books and sell
books, right? Even if you can't write a
new fantasy novel because they have the
right of first refusal and they're
sitting on your book. Um but then not
right first refusal means they can't sit
on it forever. You should be able to get
it back and then sell it. Okay. All
right. Those are your uh those are your
your your uh things to watch out for in
contracts.
Um let's go to let's go to
pitching. All
right. All right. Pitching novels. How
do you sell these days? You're going to
have to pitch your novel. Usually this
is done in the form of a query letter.
Um, I hear from a little bird that these
days query letters are often uh filled
out as a form on the agents website
rather than actually submitting
something yourself. Um, it seems like a
smart way for them to go because they
can kind of control uh how the query is
formatted and things like that. But a
query letter is
generally the about the same as what we
call an elevator pitch. These are kind
of two versions of the same thing. A um
a query letter elevator pitch is your
one paragraph pitch your best chance at
selling the
book. If you're writing one of these,
understand that one paragraph is not
enough to explain to them your whole
book. And in fact, it's not enough to
explain to them even the most all the
important points of your book. You want
to pick one thing to highlight that
makes your book stand out and pitch that
one thing. Well, I had two elevator
pictures for Misbornne. I'm going to go
over them with you. I will say upfront,
I was never great at queries. I was
during the era where you didn't need
queries. And indeed, I I submitted
queries like once or twice. Every other
submission I made was directly to the
hands of an editor. Um, and so I will
talk about that with conventions, but I
submitted to all of the big uh six back
then directly by meeting the editors and
just sending them books. Um, again, I
didn't have an agent. Um, so agents,
queries became the standard as agents
became the standard and they were
already the standard by the time I broke
in. I just knew how to because Dave
mentored me doing it the old way that
they'd done in the 80s and 90s that was
still viable and managed to slip in as
that door was closing. Okay,
so here are my pitches for Misbornne and
hopefully this can help you. I got very
good at these after I published because
I would pitch it to people in bookstores
as I was sitting there because I would
go do a book signing. My three friends
would come get a book
signed. Uh yeah, it was usually Dan and
Ben and Peter. Um, and then scar came
sometimes. Yeah. Um, and then I would
sit there cuz the signing lasted for 2
hours and I would use car salesman my
book to everybody who walked past. Uh,
some of your parents may have boughten
books from me that way. I used to be
able to say some of you, but um, yeah.
And so I got very good at pitching and
what I learned is stay away from too
many proper
nouns. Right? What you don't want is
Blorkz Zop is the the Zinglebop king of
uh
Zorkland. Uh right, don't start that
way. We're fantasy novels. We know we
like our funny names. Don't start that
way. Uh one name is fine. I would say um
I had two pitches depending on who I was
pitching to. I would kind of feel them
out as I chatted with them what they
liked and things like that. And to the
person who was hardcore science fiction
fan, I would say this is the story of
what happens when the hero
fails. What if Frodo got to the end of
Lord of the Rings with the ring and
Sauron's like, "Oh, my ring. I've been
looking for that. Thanks for that must
have been a hard journey and then killed
him and took over the
world." This story is about a gang of
thieves who live in this world who said,
"All right, the prophecies were lies.
Hero didn't save us. We're going to do
this our way. We're going to rob the
dark lord.
Silly, bribe his armies away and
overthrow the empire. Um, and so it's a
heist novel about a gang of thieves who
rob the dark lord. That's a one
paragraph pitch for Misborn, right? Um,
you can see it doesn't even mention the
names of the characters. This is a pitch
on the high concept of Misborn. This is
the you've read fantasy novels, you know
about the hero uh who saved the world.
What if that hero failed? This is that
story. Um and then it gets the it's a
mashup of a heist and an epic fantasy.
Now, if someone was more character
interested, uh if someone was younger in
particular, I would say, all right,
story about a young street thief named
Vin who finds out that the luck she's
always had is actually related to a
really cool magic system. She gets
recruited by a gang of three thieves who
are planning to rob
God and they need her to be the mole her
their mole among the nobility of this
world that worships this dark god. She
does it but she falls in love with one
of them. Boom. Right. That's that's the
uh you know and I'd say I usually said
because back then crouching tiger hidden
dragon was big. I'm like, it's a cross
between my fair lady and crouching
higher hidden dragon, right? Street
thief trained to be a noble woman while
at night she's a ninja.
Um, and so you can see how both of those
are just like one paragraph essentially.
It's a big paragraph. Starts with a good
thesis statement, right? And if you've
got a zinger, you put it right there,
right? somewhere in here, you know, it's
about the world where the hero lost and
they're going to uh gang of thieves is
going to try to rob the dark lord. Get
that in your first sentence. Expand on
it just a little bit and then end with a
zinger out. That is your query. That's
your paragraph about your book.
Otherwise, your query should include a
little bit about you. Not very much, but
a little bit about you. And usually they
recommend comp titles. Am I correct?
like this will appeal to fans of X. Um,
not the social media platform. Um, I
don't know if it has fans anymore. Um,
uh, this should appeal to fans of, uh,
and then list some several books. Piece
of advice, don't just list the most
popular books ever, right? List books
that when they read your pitch, they're
like, "Oh, I can see how that would be
similar but not the same as." Right?
pick picking good comp titles is tricky
because if you just be like this will
appeal to fans of what are the top three
books that sold this year. Um the
agent's just going to roll their eyes
and it'll be a mark against you. But if
you have if you've listed good comp
titles that the agent will know but that
aren't all you know sometimes you want
to have some good sellers but they don't
always h all have to be good sellers
then they'll understand when they read
your your pitch. That's a query. Did I
miss anything?
uh bio bio a little bit about you like I
said um if you happen to have published
in short fiction markets include that if
you're uh writing in a specialist subg
genre for instance if you're writing
military science fiction and you are a
marine include that uh Elizabeth Moon
tells the story um she's a little older
now so a lot of you won't have read her
but she's an excellent writer um uh the
story of how they didn't put that she
was ex-Marine on the back of her uh
first books and they didn't sell. As
soon as they added Marine, books just
started flying off the shelves. I'm not
sure how much that's exaggerated, but
you know, um when the readers and
editors want to know like if you're
writing hard science fiction about the
colonization of Mars and you're like,
you know, a water science um expert um
about, you know, the water, how you
would get water uh refined on Mars,
that's relevant. Um, don't put on things
that are going to make you look like
you're clout chasing. Don't be like,
"I'm a student of Brandon Sanderson."
It's not going to help you. Uh, it'll
just look like you're clout chasing. I'm
afraid. I'm sorry. Uh, if you don't have
any writing credits, just don't mention
any. Um, if you are indie published with
around 10,000 in sales, not in free
books, but actual sales, that starts to
look really good, and they will sit up
and take notice. Yeah. Would it be a bad
idea to mention like being a DM or
something? uh if you're a professional
DM or something like that. But I would,
you know, if you can work it into your
bio in a way that doesn't seem cringe,
if you're like, you know, I don't know.
I'm not sure if you can
honestly, let's be real. Um but if
you're saying a little about me, I am X
and X and I love running my uh
campaigns. Maybe like um
but yeah, be light on something that
might come off
cringe. Uh other questions? Yeah. And
for bio like leaving out the personal is
this specifically for pitches to agents
or for just general books. Oh, this is
not for your bio in your book. This is
for pitches. All of this is for pitches.
You can figure out your bio and your
books later on. I would put a GM thing
in your bio and your books. That's, you
know, that's uh flavor for who you are.
For the bio, you just want to give like
a sentence that might be relevant in
some way or just something to set you
apart. Uh if it in any way relates to
the book, include it. If it doesn't,
then don't. Like if I were Rachel and I
had a huge doll collection, I wrote the
doll makers, I would include that,
right? Um but mostly you want to keep
the bio section kind of short. Uh let
your let your book do the the talking
for you because um we'll get to outlines
and uh sample chapters. Go ahead. Do you
still have to make pitches even though
you're well? Do I have to make pitches?
Uh, I do not. Um, my pitches I'm Brandon
Sanderson,
right? Um, and that generally
works. Yeah. Um, I have to do them in
Hollywood. Hollywood doesn't care,
right? Hollywood doesn't care if you've
sold 40 million books. They're like, uh,
40 million people go see the movie, then
it's still a failure. Now, 40 million
might be okay. Uh but they know that 40
million books means 10,000 people buying
four books each more likely, right? Or
and things like that. So or really it's
like uh like a million of you buying
everything and then some buying one or
two. Uh but uh I have to do pitches a
lot in Hollywood. Um in New York I do
not have to. Um they all know that if
they don't take it, I can sell it
myself. Uh right, my secret project he's
made $10 million, right? Um, so yeah,
um, it's it's a different world, but I
did still have to pitch um, back when,
um, like even during the Wheel of Time
era when I sold Steelheart, I still did
a full pitch package and things like
that, but as I was I was talking about
uh, Rachel's asking me about it. They
got back the next day, right? Normally,
they don't get back the next day. So,
was that after the Wheel of Time when
you stopped making pitches? Yeah. Um,
basically once Stormlight came out and
sold on its own, right? I pitched
Stormlight. Every other book since then,
I just send it to the publisher and say,
"This is the one you're publishing this
year, right?" Um, and so, but that's not
unusual, right? Stephen King sends you a
book. You don't, right? John Gisham
sends you a book. Um, and I'm somewhere
in between, right? I outsell John
Gisham. I don't sell outsell Stephen
King. So, I just kind of right in
sandwiched in between those two. Yeah.
What do you put in your bio if you don't
have anything that's related to your
book? What do you put in your bio if you
don't have anything that's related? some
little flavor thing like, you know, I uh
was a CS major um and I love, you know,
Kdramas. I don't know, just something
something simple that is not going to
take a lot of attention, but that
doesn't isn't distracting, but is a
little bit distinctive for you. Does
that make sense? Who doesn't love
Kdramas, though? All right, go ahead.
How customized should a query or pitch
be based on who you're quering to?
Excellent. We'll get to that in
conventions. Okay. Um that's that's next
on the list. Yeah. In relation to
non-compete, what does it I know what a
non-compete does in like most
industries. What does that do in an
author's case? Nobody really knows
because they're uninforcable and they're
stupid. But basically, it says you can't
write books for anyone else. It's
basically a really strict first refusal
rights thing. While you're writing
publishing these books, you will not
release another book that could draw
sales away from the book that we've
released by you is basically what
they're saying. Um, and so yeah, am I
right on that? Yeah, there. So, it's
really bad, but it's really annoying.
And I know some authors that are very
annoyed by the ones in their contracts.
Yeah. Um, what would what would you know
anything about publishing in like world
English first? Yes, publishing world
English. Good question. Uh, totally
doable. You have to sell in in um in
London. Um, you I suppose could sell in
um in Australia. Um, but London's like,
so World English, my rights, they're
they sell they're about 10% of my US
rights in in sales numbers, which makes
sense because the population um of the
UK um is about 10% uh or something like
that. It that's very rough. Don't quote
me wrong on that, but you know what I
mean. Um so um Steven Ericson from
Canada sold in the UK first. It's
doable. uh if you happen to be able to
get an agent, a British agent, um or you
know, for some reason you're often in
the UK and you go to conventions over
there and you meet editors over there,
once in a while it happens. Um and so it
is it is viable particularly if you have
some contacts uh in in London and you
happen to to be there or things like
that. Uh hard to do but not impossible.
Is it only London or you said London or
Australia? I mean, Australia
technically, but to Australia has been
that fraction of population. Again, it's
almost impossible to make a living
selling only in Australia, according to
my Australian friends who have tried it.
So, basically, there are no countries
you can make a living as a science
fiction fantasy author in, except for
like so, US, UK, English, right?
Germany, you can do it. uh Poland,
Spain, like some of the very strong
European economies, you can do it. It
gets real thin after that because a lot
of the countries, like for instance, in
all of Scandinavia, they just read in
English. I don't know if you've known
people from, you know, from like Sweden,
but their English is generally better
than ours is, right? Um and so the
Swedish, um we had a guy from Iceland,
uh took my class last year. Um his his
name literally was Thor. is Gwithian
Thor. Um Thor took my class and like his
English is better than our English,
right? So you get that problem. Portugal
is about the same the same way. They
tend to read in English. Um just various
countries. You have to have a strong
local um uh reading science fiction
fantasy community. And you can kind of
tell where they are based on which like
for instance um Sepkovski is from
Poland, right? The Witcher. Uh they've
got a very Lamb is from Poland. Germany
has a bunch like um like Courtney Funka
and people like this from Germany. You
can kind of see the places where people
can make a living um at sci-fi fantasy.
But basically breaking into the US is
one of the big goals to do if you write
it cuz we read a lot of science fiction
fantasy and we are uh you know the
strongest economy in the world. So kind
of a followup. If you world English,
how hard is it to transfer? How hard is
it to transfer if you do world English
first? it can be a bit of a hiccup. Um,
so with Steven Ericson, um, he published
in the UK. People started importing his
books to the US and he had trouble
getting traction in the US because
everyone his fans were all importing and
so they would put them on shelves and
the there weren't fans to buy the new
books in the US because they already
imported them all imported them all.
That was a problem of them. us who
finally started publishing him played
catch-up and wasn't published in the new
books until like 6 months after and that
really stunted his growth but I mean
Stephen Ericson is still one of the
betterselling epic fantasy authors and
so uh that's Malazan Book of the Fallen
um if you've heard of that and again I
believe you'd have to ask him for sure I
believe he's Canadian that published in
the UK first so um all right I need to
do conventions so we're going to do one
last question do you have a quick tip
for pitching films uh pitching films Um,
yeah. I have a best-selling book. Um, I
have never to this day, okay, not never
now. Up until about my Kickstarter, I
had never had a a uh film company give
me the time of day unless they came to
me first.
Never until I had the Kickstarter. That
pushed me over the edge. before then
anything I pitched in Hollywood they
ignored me. Okay. So you have if you're
if you want to uh be in Hollywood
Michael Kiteon couldn't get any sold
until he wrote books and then sold his
books. Um you either need to go the
screenplay route and go move to
Hollywood and do that whole thing or you
need to get a bestselling book first.
Um, I would say that, you know, like
spec scripts almost never sell these
days. And if you don't have a
best-selling book, you're it's you're in
worst case. So, do not try to sell
anything to Hollywood without a book
backing it up is what I would recommend.
Okay? There's a one ina million shot you
could do it. So, don't let me crush your
dreams, but just let me tell you, like I
would go to them and I'd be like, I have
20 million sales. Here is my new book
idea. The book is coming out soon. Would
we you want to do a film deal about it?
Crickets. Um so yeah. Okay. I got to do
cons. So save grass your questions for
next week. Um or until after that. All
right. Let's talk about conventions. Uh
because uh you know and there was
another question I was going to I'm
going to get to this. If I don't get to
that other question um throw it at me
again. So do I recommend conventions and
conferences? When I was breaking in, the
way to slip in was to go to these old
conventions where, remember I told you
they started to argue about who was the
best, you know, what was the best
episode of Star Trek, right? Uh, and to
write uh Kirkbox/fic. Um, those people
all became editors or published authors
or agents. And for a long time, that was
the industry. So these conventions were
still the places they all got together
and chatted, which is why Dave said, "Go
to them. Go to the parties. sit in the
bar, chat with people, go to all the
parties, have hold a can of Sprite and
chat with people. It was actually much
less intimidating than I thought it
would be. Everyone was just like cool um
and and whatnot. And you just chatted
and uh you would I would
go to um editors and I had some magic
words which if you are so lucky maybe
you can still uh use. The wrong words
are what are you looking for? Never ask
that. The right words were, "What have
you bought recently by a new author and
why?" This gets them talking about what
they like. Why they bought this new
author's book. It gives you a book to go
read to see what that editor likes. You
legitimately are making that editor
happy because they know you're going to
go buy that book, and you should. Um,
and it's making giving you way more
information because you're hearing what
this editor liked about this book. What
I did with uh Dan and Peter is I kept a
little list of all these editors and
everyone I'd asked about. I wrote down
the books that they had bought recently
and I went and I found them and I read
them so that oh this is the question was
should you personalize and when I would
send my uh my letters to
them they would be things like I met you
at this
convention you recommended this book I
loved it. I think you'll like my book
because I do something similar to this
author in this proving I'd read their
book. That was golden, right? They loved
that. Um, and because of these sorts of
things, I was able to personalize these
letters. Doesn't work as well anymore,
but I think that could still work with
agents. I don't know. I haven't broken
in this way. There in science fiction
fantasy, um, there are two general
things. There are what we call
conferences and what we call
conventions. This is my definition.
Others may have different definitions. A
conference to me is a forprofit
institution that you pay a larger price
tag to get into and by doing so receive
professional advice from professional
authors who have been invited to
present. Agents and editors who've been
invited specifically to pre uh present
locally. You will find that at story
makers, writers for young readers, um I
think future scapes counts as well.
Okay, these are conferences. Often they
involve pitch sessions. Um you sometimes
pay for those. They are not huge
amounts, but the tickets to get into
these conventions can be expensive. Uh
you know, 600 bucks or something like
that. Um and so I looked to her cuz back
when I did it, it was cheaper. Uh but
that was you know in the stone age. Um
so that's a conference. I do recommend
conferences if you have this disposable
income to go particularly if you watch
conferences around the country for ones
inviting in agents and editors that
you've done research on that you're
interested in publishing with. You can
still skip agents this way. You can have
a pitch session with an editor and they
you will at the end of your pitch
session uh they will either say oh yeah
send me that or you can ask them would
you like to see some sample chapters
queries when you're quering it'll tell
you if they want a writing sample or not
and how much your best goal to do is to
try to get as much of your fiction into
a submission as is appropriate. Don't
send them things they're not asking for.
But you want them to read your fiction,
not your
query, right? Um, and so if they allow
you to send sample chapters, do so. Send
the beginning. When they say sample
chapters, they don't mean chapter 37 and
56. You think they're the best written.
People make that mistake a lot. Send
them what the p the audience is going to
see when they open your book. Okay? Um,
if they ask for an outline, an outline
is not an outline form as you might have
learned in school. An outline is a
twopage documentish that is uh paragraph
kind of in paragraphs explanation of the
plot of your book. This is like a
two-page pitch instead of one paragraph
pitch. In the outline, give away the
ending. Do not not put your ending in.
Your outline includes the whole book. Um
usually what you're going to look for is
you're going to look for they'll ask for
a query, three sample chapters, and an
outline. That's your package. Okay,
that's what you're wanting to send to
them. And if you are going to
conferences and meeting editors and
agents and they say, "Yeah, send me
something." That's almost certainly what
they mean. They will probably be more
explicit with you. Say, "Yeah, send me
sample chapters and outline." When they
do
that, go the next day. Don't hand it to
them in person and submit through either
the form or if they give you an email,
email it or whatever. get it to them and
put in the uh the uh the subject line
requested material because they did ask
for it. Okay. Uh if you can skip the
query only stage, you're in good shape.
Um like if you look at the stats, if you
once you like for every like hundred
queries someone gets some like every
thousand. Yeah. What's that? It's like
for every thousand they ask for sample
chapters on one or something like that.
It's just ridiculous. And if you've
already gotten there, you've just
skipped a huge hurdle in percentage. It
probably is more like one in a 100. Uh
it's probably not one in a thousand, but
I don't know. You'd have to ask agents.
So, your job is to try to skip that if
you can, if you can go to the
conferences. Conventions are different.
Conventions are these fan-run things. Uh
Life, the universe, and everything is
the local one here. Uh World Con is the
biggest of these. These are not
nonprofit run by fans to argue about
your favorite episodes of Star Trek and
these were grown up in the community
organically. A lot of authors and agents
and editors attend. They're willing to
do business at some of the at some of
the parties. That's less and less than
they used to be, but they're still
there. I will give you a
caveat. Um, when I went, I had a
wonderful time. Um, I would pitch to e
editors. It was, you know, I got very
comfortable with holding my sprite and
pitching to editors and things like
that. Um, I shared this story quite a
lot in my early days as I'm like, "This
is the way you break in." Because back
then it was. I had a female student go
to one and the very first person that
she started coding to with at one of
these at one of these parties said,
"Yeah, come back to my room. I can get
you published by tour."
No. They treat a six foot one gregarious
dude differently than they treat other
people. This has been a this is the cons
are not as bad anymore. It's been 20
years. There's been a lot of movement
toward uh separating fan spaces and
professional spaces and things like
this. But I do have to share that story.
Um and so I can't give you any more
details because I've been asked not to
share them. But um you know go with a
friend
I would always recommend going with a
friend to anything. Um, and things like
this, but um, conventions, your mileage
will vary. You still can. Brian Mlelen
sold by doing the brand and format. He
just listened to what I did. He did it a
few years. He sold. That was still back
in the early 2000s. Um, I haven't heard
of people doing it recently, but it's,
you know, anything is possible. All
right. So, there's the big um Oh, I
should mention comic cons are something
different. Ignore those for publishing.
They can be fun to go to. You will only
find publicists there. They can't buy
your book. Don't go to any comic con um
or fan expo expecting to sell your book.
They are very different. Um go to
conferences first. Maybe some
conventions of an editor's coming that
you like, but understand those are more
free form. They are not professional.
They are more fanrun. You can um you
know, your mileage may vary. All right,
we will do Q&A next week on anything you
want to ask about. Save your publishing
questions for then. Thank you all so
much. One more week.
[Applause]